A Guide to the Oswald T. Avery papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA230
Rockefeller Archive Center
Oswald T. Avery papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1913-1955
Rockefeller Archive Center
Avery, Oswald Theodore
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA230
3 Cubic Feet Extent is approximate.
Biographical/Historical note
Served
1918-1919 U.S. Army Medical Corps
1942 Member of Board for the Study and Control of Epidemic Diseases Consultant to Secretary of War National Research Council, Subcommittee on Infectious Diseases
Chronology
1877 Born October 21, Halifax, Nova Scotia
1887 Moved to New York City
1893 Graduated New York City Male Grammar School
1893-1900 Colgate Academy
1900 A.B. Colgate University
1904 M.D. College of Physicians and Surgeons, Columbia University, New York City
1904-1906 Interne, City Hospital, New York City
1906-1907 Commission for the Investigation of Acute Respiratory Diseases, Bacteriological Laboratory, College of Physicians and Surgeons
1907-1913 Hoagland Laboratory, Department of Bacteriology, Brooklyn Associate Director
1913 Assistant, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, NYC
1915 Associate, RIMR
1918 Naturalized citizen of the United States
1919 Associate Member, RIMR
1923 Member, RIMR
1943- Member Emeritus, RIMR
1949 Retired to Nashville, Tenn.
1955 Died February 20, Nashville, Tenn. Buried Mt. Olivet Cemetery
Awards
1931 John Mather Smith Prize. Columbia University (?) Value about $200. Presented to a graduate for an essay on medical research
1932 Paul Ehrlich Gold Medal. See #81 in bibliography John Phillips Memorial Award. American College or Physicians. Value of $1500. For discovery of method to pierce the protective coat of Pneumococcus. See #80 in bibliography
1944 Gold Medal of New York Academy of Medicine
1945 Copley Medal. Royal Society of London Kober Medal. Association of American Physicians
1946 Charles Mickle Fellowship. University of Toronto
1947 Lasker Award. American Public Health Association Value $1,000.
1949 Passanao Foundation Award Value $5,000.
1950 Pasteur Gold Medal. Swedish Medical Society, Stockholm
Honorary degrees
1921 Sc. D. Colgate University
1935 LL. D. McGill University
1947 Sc. D. New York University
1950 Sc. D. University of Chicago
1954 Sc. D. Rutgers University
Memberships
Society of American Bacteriologists (President 1942), Association of American Physicians, American Society for Clinical Investigations, American Society of Pathologists and Bacteriologists (President 1934), American Society for Experimental Pathology, New York Academy of Medicine, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, National Academy of Sciences (elected 1933), Harvey Society, American Public Health Association, American Association for the Advancement of Science, American Association of Immunologists (President 1923), American Association of Pathologists and Bacteriologists (President 1934)
Honorary Member: New York Academy of Sciences, 1944, Society of Experimental Biology and Medicine, Society of General Microbiology (England), Pathological Society of Great Britain and Ireland
Foreign Member: Royal Danish Academy of Science, 1951, Der Norski Videnskaps Akademi (Oslo), 1932, Académie Royale de Médecine de Belgique, 1933, Société Philomathique de Paris, The Royal Society (London), 1944
Oswald Theodore Avery, 1877-1955, physician and bacteriologist with The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, 1913-1949. Foremost researcher on pneumonia and one of the founders of the science of immunochemistry and discoverer of the transforming nature of DNA.
Scope and Contents note
Correspondence, photographs, memorabilia; reprints; bibliography.
This collection of papers of about 2½ linear feet consists primarily of memorabilia (honorary capes; medals; musical instrument) which was given to the Rockefeller University Archives by Dr. Avery's sister-in-law. It includes a small amount of administrative correspondence, photographs, bibliography and complete collection of reprints, many obituary articles and several articles about DNA. Includes photocopy of letter (1943) from Avery to his brother, Roy C. Avery, detailing his work on the transforming nature of DNA.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 Av37
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the University and of Mr. Avery's sister-in-law, Mrs. Roy C. Avery. Received or inventoried: November, 1971, June 1977.
Immunology; Bacteriology; DNA; Pneumonia; Physical Objects; Medical education; Genetics; Medical research; Medical technology; Medical sciences; Life sciences; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Biology -- Research; Biochemistry; Medicine, Preventive; Bacteria; Avery, Oswald Theodore; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- Administrative correspondence, 1913-1952; circa 1/2" (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  1913 letters between Rufus Cole and Simon Flexner with O.T. Avery application for appointment and approvals from Board Members, L. Emmett Holt and T.M. Prudden. The balance of the correspondence is primarily with the Business Manager on matters of budgeting, laboratory changes and personnel.
- Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 2)
- #2 Potter, N.B. and Avery, O.T. Opsonims and vaccine therapy In: Hare, H.A., ed. Modern treatment, Photocopies of reprints lacking in bound volumes (Box 1, Folder 2)
- #3 White, B. and Avery, O.T. Observations on certain lactic acid bacteria of the so-called Bulgaricus type, Photocopies of reprints lacking in bound volumes (Box 1, Folder 2)
- #4 Ager, L.C. and Avery, O.T. A case of influenza meningitis, Photocopies of reprints lacking in bound volumes (Box 1, Folder 2)
- #25 Avery, O.T., Dochez, A.R., and Lancefield, R.C. Bacteriology of streptococcus hemolyticus, Photocopies of reprints lacking in bound volumes (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Reports to the Board of Scientific Directors or the Corporation (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1932 January 16, Typescript signed, 2 pp.
  - 1941, Duplicated copy, 7 pp.
  - 1942, Duplicated copy, 1 1/2 pp.
  - 1943, Duplicated copy, 5 1/2 pp.
- Congratulatory message from F. Neufeld on winning Ehrlich medal, 12/20/1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Citation on American College of Physicians, 1932 award of John Phillips Memorial Prize (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Science, p. 329 Citation on award of Gold Medal of The New York Academy of Medicine, 1944 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Nature, p. 694. Citation on award of Copley Medal, 1945 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Newspaper articles on awards, 1932-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence (4) requests for publicity material to be used on winning of Lasker Award, American Public Health Association, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- News release material on $5,000 award of Passano Foundation, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letter, Avery to American Ambassador to Sweden on acceptance of Pasteur Medal in Avery's behalf, 1950 November 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Summaries of work; obituaries; articles (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Summary of work on transformation prepared for H.S. Gasser by F.L. Horsfall, R.D. Hotchkiss, and René Dubos, 1952 January 16; typescript 9 pp.
  - Memorial Minute, 1955; Duplicated copy 5 pp.
  - News release prepared by T.M. Rivers for newspaper obituary notices, 1955 February 21; Duplicated copy 2 1/2 pp.
  - NEW YORK HERALD obituary, 1955 February 22
  - Lomholt, A. (Danish Academy) to E.B. Smith verifying obituary notice, 1955 May 27
  - Record of floral sprays sent for funeral by RI people
- Obituary articles (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chesney, Alan M. IN MEMORIUM. Journal of pathology and bacteriology 74 (1957 (451-460)
  - Hotchkiss, Rollin D. OSWALD T. AVERY, 1877-1955
  - Genetics 51 (1965) 1-10
  - Dubos, R.J. OSWALD THEODORE AVERY Biographical memoirs of the Fellows of The Royal Society 2 (1956) 35-48, 1877-1955
  - MacLeod, Colin. OBITUARY ARTICLE, OSWALD THEODORE AVERY, 1877-1955. Journal of general microbiology 17 (1957) 539-549
- Articles (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Stanley, Wendell M. The "undiscovered" discovery. Archives of environmental health 21 (1970) 256-262
  - Wyatt, H.V. How history has blended. Nature 249 (1974) 803-805
  - Cohen, Jack. Chapter VII: Genetic transformation by DNA in: A GENERATION OF DNA
    Unpublished. Received for publication permission January 1976.
  - M.D. Remembers: A pioneer in DNA research. Medical news magazine, March 1977, 72, 1977 March
- Letter from Harold C. Anderson to René Dubos on personal recollection, 1977 April 18; Photocopy, 2 pp. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Tennessee State Library and Archives (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Inventory of Avery papers in the Manuscript Unit. 600 items and two volumes. Includes vita and bibliography as per record.
  Folder includes two photocopies of letter written 13 May 1943 to brother Roy (Original with Tennessee State Library papers) detailing work on transformation factor and recognition of importance. One photocopy supplied by Dr. M. McCarty with typescript translation of handwritten letter.
- Photographs, 1984 (Box 1)
  Includes official RIM portraits by Louis Schmidt; snap shots by Dr. W. Goebel in laboratory and includes colleagues; a number of family photographs supplied by Mrs. Roy Avery to René Dubos for THE PROFESSOR, THE INSTITUTE AND DNA and given to the archives by Dr. Dubos. Also negatives with prints of exhibit prepared to commemorate 100th anniversary of O.T. Avery birth.
- Annals of Science: DNA 3 part article from THE NEW YORKER 1978 Nov. 27, Dec. 4 and 11 by Horace Freeland Judson (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Memorabilia, 1½ linear feet Paige box (Box 2)
  - Honorary hoods
    - Colgate University, 1921
    - McGill University, 1935
    - New York University, 1947
    - University of Chicago, 1950
    - Rutgers University, 1954
  - Medals
    - American College of Physicians, 1932
    - Paul Ehrlich Gold Medal, 1932
    - Gold Medal New York Academy of Medicine, 1944
    - Copley Medal. Royal Society of London, 1945
    - Kober Medal. Association of American Physicians, 1945
    - Pasteur Gold Medal, 1950
  - Assorted items
    - Delta Kappa Epsilon fraternity pin
    - Phi Beta Kappa key 1900
    - Caduceus (pair) U.S. Army Silver encased thermometer (engraved: 1906 New York City Training School)
    - Pince nez in case
    - Silver cornet (engraved with name and date)
- Photograph by O.T. Avery. Sunset on Deer Island, Maine, 1930s; Package 23 × 19 x½ (Package 1)
- Water color by O.T. Avery (after Cook), 1932 August (Package 1)
- Collected reprints, 3 volumes (Box 2)
  - Volume 1, 1909-1918
  - Volume 2, 1919-1924
  - Volume 3, 1925-1946
- Griffith, Fred. The significance of the pneumococcal types. Journal of Hygiene 27 (1927/1928) pp. 113-159, 1 volume (Box 2)
  Bound 1979 with note from Joshua Lederberg.
- Lewis Thomas. "Oswald Avery and the Cascade of Surprises. "ESQUIRE 100 No. 6 (December 1983) 74-78, 1983 December; 1 bound volume in 2-1/2" Hollinger Box (Box 3)
- Avery photographs, Photographs and negatives
  - Avery in uniform, circa 1918 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Avery - early Louis Schmidt portrait (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Avery - portrait sittings, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Avery - portrait sittings, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Avery - portrait sitting, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 4a)
  - Group photos of Avery department, circa 1932 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Walther F. Goebel snapshots of Avery in lab, 1930s (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Avery - Miscellaneous photos of Avery in lab (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Avery in garden and with colleague's child (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Avery - Family photos and Colgate University photos (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Avery - Paintings (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Avery Gateway (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Includes photos of Drs. Macleod and McCarty.
  - Avery - Centennial RU Archives Exhibit 1977 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Correspondence between Marjory Stephenson and Sir Walter Fletcher from Archives of the Medical Research Council, London, 1931; Photocopies
  This correspondence was cited in Robert E. Kohler, "Innovation in Normal Science. Bacterial Physiology" Isis 76: 162-181 (June 1985), and requested from MRC Archives at suggestion of Dr. Lederberg. Includes Stephenson/Fletcher, 8 Nov 1931, re visit to America and meeting Avery and Heidelberger.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Received September 1985.